My beloved father tried to save me from drowning in a nearby river,
我在附近的河里差点溺水 我亲爱的父亲试着救我
and he died instead.
结果他死了
Ever since then, my mother harbored resentment in her heart
从此以后 我母亲对我心怀怨恨
towards me for killing her dear husband,
认为我害死了她心爱的丈夫
and started to avoid me.
开始避着我
"It's all because of your smile."
“都是因为你的笑容
"Your smile brings misfortune to everyone around you."
你的笑容会给你身边 所有人带来不幸”
She always reprimanded me.
她总是责怪我
And then, I met my husband.
然后我遇见了我丈夫
I gave birth to a boy who looked just like him.
我生下一个长得很像他的男孩
When I see the both of them eating and praising my cooking,
当我看见他们两人 吃我煮的东西 赞美我的厨艺时
I was so happy every day,
就让我的每一天洋溢着幸福
and I lived on as I smiled from the bottom of my heart.
在生活中发自内心露出笑容
My husband told him, "Never come back here again."
我丈夫告诉他“永远不要再回来”
and my brother flew into a rage.
我弟弟大发雷霆
He said, "It's your fault. You seduced me."
他说“这是你的错 是你引诱我的”
And he set our house on fire.
然后他放火烧我们的家
As the flames grew bigger,
随着火势越来越大
I could hear someone shout, "Save me, Mom! Save me!"
我能听到有人大喊 “救我 妈妈 救我”
It was my son screaming.
那是我儿子在大喊
My mother and my husband's parents told me...
我妈妈和我的公婆告诉我
"Enough with the apologies."
“不要再道歉了
"You don't have to do anything."
你什么也不用做
"Just don't smile until you die."
到死前都不要笑就好了”
I talked about everything regarding myself.
我说出了关于我的一切
As promised...
依照承诺
I will now quit my job.
我现在就辞职
Why are you guys still up?
你们怎么还没睡？
That's our line, Dad.
你还不是一样
Well...
没有啦
I just couldn't get myself to sleep.
我睡不着
Us, too.
我们也是
Mita's really not coming.
三田小姐果然没出现
Maybe she won't come back to our house anymore.
她大概不会再来我们家了
I really regret asking her
早知道当初
now that this happened.
就不要追问她的往事了
I'll try calling her again.
我再试着打电话联络她
The number you reached is currently not available.
您拨的电话无法接听…
How did it go, Dad?
爸爸 怎么样？
She rejected my calls.
她拒绝接我电话
Dear me...
唉唷
Akari finally confessed everything?
灯子都告诉你们了吗？
It was such a huge shock, we were at a loss for words.
她的发言让人太过震惊 我们全都目瞪口呆
Here you go. Have some.
请用茶
Thanks.
不好意思
Well...
这个嘛…
I think it has been almost 30 years since Akari's mother remarried.
距离灯子的妈妈再婚 已经过了快30年了
I went to their family to work as their housekeeper.
我当时在他们家担任家政妇
She always tried her best to smile, even when she was lonely.
不管灯子当时有多寂寞 她都努力挤出笑容
When I gave her a monaka for the first time,
我第一次给她最中饼时
it wasn't even a big deal.
那只是件不值一提的小事
But she was all happy and said, "I love monaka!"
她却对我说“我最喜欢最中饼了”
She looked so happy. Here you go.
一脸心花怒放 请用
MONAKA
（小仓最中饼）
Excuse me...
请问…
Could you ask Mita to come back to work for us again?
您可以拜托三田小姐 请她回我们家工作吗？
The kids want her back, too.
孩子们也希望她回来
But she doesn't want it.
如果她本人不愿意
So it's not something I can do.
我也没办法勉强她
Please do something about it.
请您设法说服她
It's all thanks to Mita that our family wasn't torn apart.
多亏三田小姐 我们家才没有分崩离析
We need Mita in our family.
我们一家人需要三田小姐
Please.
拜托您
I beg you!
请您帮帮忙
Excuse me, but have you seen the lady
不好意思 请问你有没有看到
-who's always here by herself? -What?
-那位总是独自前来的女客人 -什么？
She always wears a down jacket and a cap,
那个女人总是穿着羽绒衣 戴着帽子
orders a family set meal and goes back without touching it.
她总是点家庭套餐 回去时餐点却原封不动
That lady! She hasn't been here recently.
我知道了 她最近都没有出现
Is that so... Thank you.
这样啊 谢谢你
No problem.
不客气
Come on. You don't have to be in such a rush.
看吧 就叫你吃慢一点了
Slow down. Is it good?
慢慢来 好吃吗？
Mita always came here
三田小姐总是来这里
to mourn for her late husband and son,
缅怀她过世的丈夫和孩子
I guess.
应该是这样吧
What does "mourn" mean?
“缅怀”是什么意思？
Means you remember someone who died and get sad over it.
回想死去的人 陷入悲伤
It's from Dad.
是爸爸
Hello?
喂？
No way! Really?
不会吧 真的吗？
What's going on, Yui?
姐姐 怎么了？
He says Mita is coming from tomorrow!
三田小姐明天开始会来上班
Ten seconds.
倒数十秒
Eight, seven, six, five...
-八、七、六、五…
four, three, two, one, zero!
-四、三、二、一、零
No way. Mita didn't come!
不会吧 三田小姐根本没出现
-Not that I could do anything about it. -Man...
-跟我抱怨也没用啊 -真是的
I'll get the door!
我去开门
See? Didn't I tell you?
看吧 爸爸没骗你们
I'm Mita, the housekeeper.
我是家政妇 我姓三田
I am here on behalf of Harumi Housekeeping Agency.
是晴海家政妇介绍所指派我来的
What?
-什么？
Wow, you have so many wonderful kids.
唉唷 这么多乖巧的孩子
The last household I worked in only had one son and daughter,
我之前工作的家庭 有一对大小姐和小少爷
and they were so spoiled.
两个人都被宠坏了
Oh, give us a moment.
是 请稍等我一下
Excuse me, but what's going on?
不好意思 请问到底是怎么回事？
Sorry, but I asked Akari about it.
抱歉 我询问灯子后
She said she doesn't want to work for you anymore.
她表示不想再到府上工作了
In her stead,
为了取代她
I got another housekeeper who has the same last name as her.
我找了相同姓氏的三田小姐
But that's hardly the same...
只是姓氏一样…
Don't worry! She's really diligent too!
完全不用担心 这位三田小姐也很勤奋
By the way, her first name is Tami.
顺带一提 她的名字叫做田三
So her name's Mita even if you read it backwards.
所以就算倒着念 她的名字依然是三田
Don't get her name wrong.
别搞错喔
Got it. Well, I'm sorry,
我知道了 但是很抱歉
but we don't intend on getting someone else as the housekeeper.
我不打算让其他家政妇在我家工作
Could you ask Mita...
可以请您设法派三田小…
I mean, Akari Mita, to come over?
三田灯小姐来我家工作吗？
About that...
这个嘛…
Akari's already doing that.
灯子现在已经没办法了
What do you mean?
没办法？
She's already decided to work for another household.
她已经决定要去别的家工作了
What?
什么？
Well then, please excuse me.
那么我先告辞了
I'm truly sorry about this.
真的很抱歉
No, it's quite all right.
没关系 别放在心上
She got her here just because they share the same last name?
竟然因为她也姓三田 就派她过来
Ms. Harumi's really sloppy in her work.
那位所长还真随兴
-Daddy. -Yes?
-爸爸 -怎么了？
Will we never see Mita again?
我们再也见不到三田小姐了吗？
Our only choice is to go visit Mita ourselves!
到了这个地步 我们只能直接去见三田小姐了
But how?
你要怎么去见她？
Well, we'll ask for Mita's current workplace.
请所长告诉我 她为哪户人家工作
We can't do that.
这是不可能的
It'll cause trouble for that family, too.
这会造成别人家的困扰
Then what? Are we going to give up?
那我们该怎么办？直接放弃吗？
Calm down, Kakeru. We're running out of time today,
小翔 冷静一点 时间来不及了
so let's head to school.
你该去上学了
Yes, you're right. I have to find a job soon, too.
就是说啊 爸爸也必须赶快找工作
All right, let's go.
好 大家走吧
Okay.
好
Huh? Where's my handphone?
怪了 我的手机去哪了？
What time will you come home today?
你今天大概几点回家？
How should I know that?
我怎么知道？
Oh, good morning.
大家早安
Hey, did you see my husband's handphone?
我问你 你看到我老公的手机了吗？
I found it.
看到了
Thanks.
谢谢
Mr. Minagawa.
主人
What is it?
怎么了？
Your necktie's crooked.
你的领带歪掉了
Oh...
这样啊
Well then, I'm leaving.
那我出门了
Have a safe trip.
路上小心
Hey. Stop spacing out
别呆站在那里
and help out with all the household chores.
快来打扫家里
As you wish.
我知道了
Wait, Mita!
等一下 三田小姐
I will be working next to your family from today onwards.
我从今天开始为隔壁工作
I'm Mita, their housekeeper.
我是三田 他们的家政妇
MISAWA KINDERGARTEN
（三泽幼儿园）
Mommy!
妈咪
Hey, Mita.
三田小姐
Let's go, Tsubasa.
小翼先生 我们回家吧
You're so late! You should be the first one here to fetch me home.
动作真慢 你必须第一个来接我啊
I'm sorry.
很抱歉
Your hand feels cold, Mita.
三田 你的手好冰
Mita.
三田小姐
Why are you working for our next door neighbor?
你怎么在隔壁工作？
Please! Come back home.
拜托你回我们家
I'm sorry, but I'm no longer related to your family.
很抱歉 我已经与各位毫无瓜葛了
Then at least pick up our calls!
你至少该接我们的电话吧
Don't reject our calls please!
拜托你别设拒接
Or at least let us send you texts.
至少让我们发短信给你
I'm sorry, but I have already deleted all your numbers.
很抱歉 我已经删除府上的电话了
I'm home. Woah!
我回来…吓死我了
What's going on with you guys?
你们在做什么？
She's here again!
她又跑来了
Who?
谁啊？
Don't tell me... It's Urara?
难道是小丽吗？
I told her that Mita quit,
我告诉她三田小姐辞职后
and she said, "I'll come cook for you guys every day!"
她就说“那我要每天来煮饭”
What?
什么？
Welcome home, Keiichi. Dinner will be done in a moment...
姐夫 你回来啦 饭快煮好了…
Wait, Urara...
等一下 小丽…
Sorry, but I'll eat those I dropped on the floor.
抱歉 掉地上的份就留给我吃吧
You don't have to do this. You're busy with work already.
你不需要这么做 工作很忙吧？
I'm fine. I'm doing this to make up for
别担心 我想跟大家赔罪
the party we were supposed to hold for Dad.
毕竟上次没庆祝爸爸出院
Remember? We couldn't get the dinner reservation.
还记得吗？上次没预约到餐厅
No, that's all right.
别放在心上
You also need to save on living expenses
姐夫 你找到工作前
until you find a job, too.
必须拮据度日
You're not in the position to hire a housekeeper.
现在没有闲钱雇用家政妇吧？
True, but...
话虽如此…
Oh, no!
糟糕
I put it in for too long!
我把时间设得太久了
It's getting burnt!
糟糕 焦掉了
That was dangerous!
危险
Hey. What should we do?
喂 我们该怎么办？
We had something prepared just in case.
我们姑且有个预备方案
What? What did you guys do?
什么方案？
He should be here any minute.
他应该很快就会出现了
Grandpa's here!
外公来了
Hey, Urara! What are you doing here?
小丽 你在这里做什么？
That's my line. Why are you here, Dad?
是我该问你吧 你怎么来了？
I'm here to bring you back, obviously!
这还要说吗？我来带你回去
Stop it! I'm still preparing dinner.
别这样 我还要准备晚餐
Why are you making dinner here
你抛下自己家不管
while there's nothing at home?
跑来别人家煮饭？
Don't get in my way! I'm doing this since they're having trouble here!
别妨碍我 因为大家很苦恼 我才过来帮忙
Why don't you read the atmosphere?
拜托你察言观色一下 好吗？
Can't you tell you're causing trouble for them?
是你造成他们的困扰 看不出来吗？
Oh...
这样啊…
Well...
那个…
Sorry, Urara.
小丽 抱歉喔
We appreciate your thought, but...
你的好意我们心领了
We'll deal with dinner ourselves.
我们会自己准备晚餐
I'm really sorry.
真的很抱歉
No, I should be sorry for doing this all the time.
我也很抱歉 总是自作主张
See you.
我先走了
I'm going back now.
我回去了
Well, I'm going back too.
我也回去了
Thanks, Grandpa.
外公 谢谢
Sorry about this, father-in-law.
岳父 不好意思
Everyone. You may think I'm just spoiling my daughter,
各位可能觉得我很宠女儿
but Urara's just desperate to do anything to care for your family.
但小丽只是想要全心全意地照顾你们
So please forgive her, as it were.
希望各位原谅她喔
We understand, as it were!
我们当然清楚喔
Oh!
这样啊
Thank you, as it were!
谢谢喔
We got it. Thank you.
-那我走了 -不好意思
Well then, let's eat.
大家开始吃吧
-Thank you for the food.
-我开动了
We can't eat Mita's cooking anymore.
再也吃不到三田小姐的料理了
But why would she work for the family next door?
她为什么会到隔壁工作？
Could she just want to be near us
其实她很担心我们
since she's worried about us?
所以她想待在附近守护我们
I don't think it's that simple.
我觉得事情没这么单纯
I have a bad feeling about this.
我有种不好的预感
I think it's strange that Mita always does anything we ask.
三田小姐总是答应我们的各种要求 让我感到不可思议
But after hearing her confession the other day,
听到三田小姐上次的告白后
I was thinking that
我猜她…
maybe she wants to self-destruct.
说不定想要自我毁灭
What does "self-destruct" mean?
什么是“自我毁灭”？
It means that she wants to kill herself,
就是想要自杀
or willingly accept the death sentence.
或是接受死刑
That's why she agreed to walk into the river with Kii without any hesitation.
所以她才毫不犹豫地 牵着希衣走进河里
And also why she tried to kill Kaito's classmate?
或是企图杀害海斗的同学
So...
三田小姐…
Mita's working for Tsubasa's family so that she can self-destruct?
她是为了自我毁灭 才到小翼家工作吗？
The old hag next door seems like she'd ask her to do dangerous things.
隔壁的大婶感觉会要求她 做些危险的事
Since her husband's having an affair.
毕竟她老公有小三
Hey. What should we do, Dad?
爸爸 怎么办？
That is...
这个嘛…
something you should decide for yourselves.
必须由你们自己决定
Just kidding!
开玩笑的啦
Why are you imitating Mita?
你干吗模仿三田小姐啊？
Sorry about that. Still...
抱歉 但是…
When I look at you guys,
我觉得你们几个…
I feel really reassured.
感觉很可靠
As if you guys would be able to protect Mita.
我觉得你们一定有办法保护三田小姐
What kind of irresponsible statement is that?
真是不负责任的发言
I told you guys why Yui was given her name, right?
我把小结这个名字的由来 告诉过你们吧
Because I can bring the family back together
当家庭分崩离析时
if we ever separated, right?
我能让大家团结在一起 对吧？
Yes.
没错
In fact, your mom came up with all your names.
其实你们的名字都是妈妈取的
Really? Then what about my name?
真的吗？那我名字的涵意呢？
"I want Kakeru to become someone
“当家人陷入苦恼时
who will come to rescue our family immediately
希望小翔能成为
if we ever get into trouble."
立刻飞奔到家人身边的人”
Then what about me?
那我呢？
"I want Kaito to become someone
“我希望海斗长大后
who can provide solutions for our family."
能帮家人找出答案”
What? Was my name supposed to be a pun?
所以我的名字是个双关语啊
What about me?
我呢？
"In English, Kii means Key.
“希衣的名字发音与英文的钥匙相同
So, Kii will be the key that opens the door of happiness for our family."
所以她能为家人打开一扇幸福之门”
Okay! I'll do my best!
我知道了 我会加油
If the four of you work together, you can do anything.
只要你们同心协力 就所向无敌
What? Are you not planning to do anything, Dad?
什么嘛 你打算什么都不做吗？
For now, I'll have to do my best in my job.
我必须先努力工作
What? You found a job?
什么？你找到工作了吗？
Well, yeah.
是啊
-Good work today.
-辛苦了
Good work today.
辛苦了
You too.
你也是
You're quite the odd one.
你还真奇怪
You were an elite employee in a first-rate company,
你本来是一流企业的精英
yet you want to work at subcontractors like us.
却跑来我们这种外包商工作
-Oh... -Oops, I made a typo.
-这个… -糟糕 打错字了
Well, I have my reasons.
我也有自己的苦衷
Huh?
奇怪
-What's the matter, Urara? -Well...
-小丽 你怎么在这里？ -那个…
I heard from Yui that you got a job, Keiichi.
小结在学校告诉我 你找到工作了
If you'd like, I bought lunch for you.
我买了午餐给你
Oh, thanks.
谢谢
I'm sorry about yesterday, Keiichi.
姐夫 昨天很抱歉
You don't have to.
别在意
We're grateful that you always worry about us, Urara.
谢谢你总是担心我们
Hey... A gift for you?
唉唷 有人送礼物给你吗？
-Are you two lovebirds? -No, that's not it...
-两位是情侣吗？ -不…
-Are you two love-dovey? -That's not... Oh!
-不是的 -你们在交往…糟糕
-Sorry. -It's all right!
-抱歉 -没关系
In any case, I'm sure you two are lovers!
所以你们确实在交往 没错吧？
How lovey-dovey! All right, time to eat!
真是甜蜜蜜 好 我要去吃饭了
Hey. Why are you working in a place like this?
姐夫 你怎么在这种地方工作？
Well, it was my dream to work for a major construction company
我的梦想本来就是 在大型建设公司工作
and build big buildings and bridges.
搭建大楼或桥梁
This is a good chance for me,
这是个好机会
so I wanted to start from scratch.
我也打算再次从零开始努力
Is there anything I can help?
我能帮得上忙吗？
What?
什么？
Well... I'll just appreciate the thought.
没有啦 你的好意我心领了
I guess Mita's probably way more useful than me.
三田小姐果然比我可靠吧？
No, that's not true.
没这回事
But I do want you to come visit us again, for the sake of the kids.
希望你能看在孩子的份上 再次拜访我家
You know...
你知道…
I think you guys should stop getting involved with that person.
我希望你们别再跟那个人来往了
I think she's strange, and she seems dangerous too.
那个人有点古怪 感觉很危险
What's going to happen if she has a crime record?
如果她有前科怎么办？
Mita's not that kind of person.
三田小姐不是那种人
What?
什么？
That person has circumstances far beyond your imagination, Urara.
她有你难以想象的苦衷
What do you mean?
什么意思？
Well, that's...
这个嘛…
Let's have a talk again soon. Thanks for the lunch.
下次再跟你慢慢聊 谢谢你的午餐
Hey, what are you guys up to?
你们几个在做什么？
Perfect timing, Yui! We thought about it,
姐姐 你来得正好 我们思考过了
and the only way
让三田小姐回来的方法
is to make Mita get fired so that she will come back!
就是让邻居开除她
What?
什么？
We asked the lady at the housekeeping agency.
我去问了介绍所的大婶
The top three reasons why housekeepers get fired are
家政妇被开除的前三大原因
when they're bad at chores,
第一是家事做得不好
when they have an affair with the husband
第二是跟家里主人偷情
and when they're suspected of stealing.
第三是主人怀疑家政妇偷窃家中物品
The first two reasons won't work,
我们没办法达成前两个原因
so we're thinking of trying the third one.
打算从第三个原因下手
Huh? What do you mean?
什么？什么意思？
MINAGAWA RESIDENCE
（皆川家）
Excuse me!
有人在吗？
What do you need?
您有什么事吗？
Excuse me, is Tsubasa in?
请问小翼在家吗？
You have visitors, Tsubasa.
小翼先生 有客人找您
Let's hang out, Tsubasa!
小翼 我来找你玩
Can we come play with you, too?
我们也可以跟你一起玩吗？
I heard your mom isn't around today!
听说你妈妈出门了
Hey, you guys!
等一下 你们几个…
Here you go.
请用
Thanks.
谢谢
Why don't we play a game, Tsubasa?
小翼 我们来玩游戏吧
The one that you like.
玩你喜欢的游戏
Sure.
好啊
Wow!
天啊
-You're really good. -You're good at this.
-真有一套 -你真厉害
Say, Tsubasa.
小翼 问你一下
Where does your mom place her valuables?
你妈妈最珍惜的东西放在哪里啊？
I don't know.
我不知道
What about things like her jewels and rings?
像是她的珠宝或戒指
Over there.
在那里
Okay.
好
Here it is!
有了
Isn't this a bad idea?
这样还是不太好吧？
It'll be fine.
放心啦
We'll just return it after Mita gets fired.
三田小姐被开除后 我们还给她就是了
I'm home, Tsubasa!
小翼 我回来了
Wait, what are you guys doing?
等一下 你们在这里做什么？
Well, we're here to play with Tsubasa.
那个 我们来找小翼一起玩
We wanted to tour your house too, since it looks really great.
我们顺便来参观您家 因为这里太气派了
Enough. Just go home already.
够了 给我离开这里
Tsubasa has to study since his entrance exams are next year.
小翼明年要考试 必须乖乖念书
Mita.
三田
Didn't I tell you not to let anyone in while I'm away?
我吩咐过你吧？ 我离开时不准让外人进来
I'm sorry.
很抱歉
You guys!
你们几个
What happened, Mita?
三田小姐 发生什么事了？
Could you please warn your siblings to never come here again?
可以叮咛你的弟弟们 请他们别再过来吗？
Ms. Minagawa ordered me to not let you guys enter.
夫人下了命令 不准各位进来这个家
Oh, I'm sorry.
对不起喔
But Kakeru and the others just want to do something for you, Mita.
但他们只是想帮你
Please, Mita. Just come back to our house!
三田小姐 拜托你回来我们家吧
Tell us. Why are you working for this family?
告诉我们 你为什么 要在这种地方工作？
I'm worried about you, Mita!
三田小姐 我很担心你
Please excuse me.
先失陪了
You don't even understand this, Tsubasa?
小翼 你连这种问题都不会吗？
Do this next.
接下来做这一题
Tsubasa.
小翼
Call Papa and tell him this.
你打电话给爸爸
"I don't understand an exam question,
告诉他“考试问题解不出来
so come back home early and teach me."
快点回家教我”
What? Again?
什么？又要联络爸爸？
Don't say that. Do it.
别抱怨了 动作快
I don't want to!
我不要
Hey!
等一下
I'll go pee!
我要尿尿！
What do you want?
怎么了？
What should I do about Mr. Minagawa's dinner?
请问该怎么处理主人的晚餐？
What?
什么？
If I don't know when he will come back,
像今天这样 不知道他是否回家用餐时
I cannot waste the food that I prepared.
我不能浪费准备好的食物
You don't need to be concerned about that.
别担心这么多
Just clean it up.
拿去处理掉
Understood.
我知道了
Hey...
我问你
You were saying something strange the other day,
你上次说过奇怪的话
but is it true?
那是真的吗？
What do you mean?
奇怪的话？
You said that he was on the phone with another woman,
你说我先生在跟其他女人打电话
and that he's planning to divorce me.
还说要跟我离婚
If you suspect...
如果您对他有所怀疑
Then why don't you confirm it yourself?
您可以当面询问他
There's no way I can ask my husband if he's having an affair.
就算我问他 他也不可能据实以告
I don't want to be so pathetic that I'd stoop to checking his phone.
我也不想像个可悲的妻子 检查他的手机
Besides...
再说…
It's true that he's popular with woman,
那个人确实很有女人缘
but we were so madly in love.
但我们谈过一场轰轰烈烈的恋爱
When he proposed to me,
他求婚时
he said that he will only love me.
承诺过这辈子只爱我一个人
There's no way someone like him would betray me.
那样的人不可能背叛我
If you have no other matters,
如果没有其他事情要处理
I would like to take my leave since it's time.
我的勤务时间已经到了 先下班了
Wait a minute.
等一下
You will really...
只要是我吩咐的事情
do anything I ask, right?
你真的都会乖乖照办吧？
If it is within my means.
如果我做得到的话
Then could you tail my husband tomorrow?
那你明天可以去跟踪我老公吗？
He said he has a golf business meeting, but who knows if it's true.
他说他要招待客户打高尔夫 我不知道他是否说了实话
If he happens to be with a woman,
如果他跟女人在一起
I want you to investigate her, too.
希望你能调查那个女人的身份
As you wish.
我知道了
Papa's home!
爸爸回来了
-Really? -I bought cake, Tsubasa!
-是吗？ -小翼 我买了蛋糕
-Welcome home, Papa! -Welcome home.
-爸爸 你回来啦 -我回来了
You're late today again.
你今天也好晚回家
I told you, it's busy at work lately.
我告诉过你吧 我这阵子很忙
I will be taking my leave, Mr. Minagawa.
主人 我先告辞了
Oh. Why don't you join us for some cake, Mita?
三田小姐 你要不要一起吃蛋糕？
No, I'm fine.
不用了
Take care.
路上小心
I said you didn't have to see me off.
我告诉过你吧 不用每次都出来送我
I'm counting on you.
拜托你了
Understood.
我知道了
After that, your husband picked up a young woman from an apartment in Aoyama
后来主人前往青山的公寓 迎接一位年轻女性
and headed for the golf course in Izu.
前往伊豆的高尔夫球场
They shared random puns, like "Aw, you dummy. I'll have a hole-in-one
和对方开着无聊的玩笑 像是“我今天要和你一杆进洞”等等
with you today" as they enjoyed their time playing golf.
开心地打了两个回合
They returned to Tokyo after that,
打完高尔夫后 两人返回东京
and thoroughly enjoyed food and wine
在西麻布的高级餐厅
at a high-class restaurant in Nishi-azabu.
享受美食与美酒
Mr. Minagawa was slightly drunk as he left the restaurant,
微醺的主人步出餐厅后
kissing the woman several times while they were walking
在路上数度与对方接吻
and said, "It's been years since I slept in the same room as my wife.
表示自己好几年没跟老婆同床共枕
In fact, I regret marrying her.
相当后悔娶了她
I would divorce her immediately if we didn't have a child,
要不是为了孩子 早就离婚了
but it makes me so mad to think that I have to pay for
想到妻子会得到赡养费和房子 就很不甘心
the alimony fees and give her the house, so I can't divorce her."
没办法离婚
And then, they disappeared into a hotel.
然后两人消失在常去的酒店里
Also...
还有…
What is it? There's still more?
怎么了？还有什么吗？
This is receipt for the taxi fee.
这是计程车的收据
I don't need that!
我不需要那种东西
Just what's going on?
到底是怎么回事？
Just what have I worked so hard for?
我为什么要这么辛苦？
Mita...
三田…
I have a request.
我要拜托你一件事
Yes?
是
Could you kill my husband tomorrow?
你明天…
Is that an order?
这是工作上的命令吗？
That's right.
对
As you wish.
我知道了
Wait.
等一下
Maybe I should die too.
我也要一起死
Right. I think that's better.
没错 这样比较好
If that's the case, I can't leave Tsubasa alone.
我们不能丢下小翼
Then... I'm bringing the whole family with me.
既然如此 我们全家都去死吧
Tomorrow, could you burn down this house
明天你可以烧掉这栋房子
together with our entire family?
还有我们一家三口吗？
As you wish.
我知道了
When you turn at the tree
在树的地方转弯
And walk straight
然后继续前进
Your beloved home is there waiting for you
你可爱的家在等着你
Yui. It's Tsubasa's birthday today.
姐姐 今天是小翼的生日
Oh, really?
是吗？
He was really happy.
他很开心喔
His mommy told him that she'll buy anything he wants.
因为他妈妈说 他想要的东西都会买给他
He doesn't need to attend violin lesson,
他不用去上小提琴课
and doesn't need to study for exams anymore!
也不用参加考试了
Is that so?
这样啊？
Mita!
三田小姐
Mita? I heard that it's Tsubasa's birthday today.
三田小姐 我听说今天是小翼的生日
Huh? So what's the problem?
什么？那是怎么回事？
Don't you think it's strange?
你不觉得奇怪吗？
She suddenly told her child that
她突然告诉小孩
he doesn't need to go learn violin or study.
不用去学小提琴 也不用参加考试
That old hag was so strict about her child's education,
毕竟隔壁的大婶为了教育孩子
like her life depended on it.
相当拼命
Don't tell me...
她该不会…
She's not planning to die, is she?
想要寻死吧？
What?
什么？
Kii. I need you to help me.
希衣 帮我一个忙
-Good evening!
-晚安
What is it? I told you guys not to come here again.
你们来做什么？ 我告诉过你们不准再来我家
Well, Kii brought a present for Tsubasa since it's his birthday.
希衣说今天是小翼生日 我们带了礼物过来
Are you there, Tsubasa?
小翼在吗？
-Happy birthday! -Hey!
-生日快乐 -等一下
What is it?
怎么了？
Happy birthday, Tsubasa!
小翼 祝你生日快乐
-I don't need things like this. -What?
-我不需要这种东西 -什么？
Hey, what did you do?
等一下 你搞什么啊？
Could you kids just go home already?
够了 你们回家吧
Don't say that! We want to celebrate his birthday!
别这样嘛 我们也想庆祝他的生日
We only celebrate birthdays with our family members.
我们只跟家人庆祝生日
Ms. Minagawa! You didn't ask Mita to do anything strange, right?
阿姨 你没有拜托三田小姐 做些奇怪的事情吧？
-What are you saying? -If you did, tell her to stop.
-你在胡说什么啊？ -希望你不要这么做
Mita will really do anything dangerous you tell her to do!
不管你交代三田小姐 做多么危险的事 她都会去做的
It's none of your business!
不关你们的事
Mita!
三田小姐
Please! Stop doing anything dangerous!
拜托你别做出危险的事
We beg you, Mita!
拜托你了 三田小姐
Come home!
回来吧
Just leave! You're going hurt your fingers!
真受不了 小心门会夹到手
You're in the way! Leave!
别碍事 滚回去
Dinner is ready.
晚餐准备好了
Did something happen? It was noisy earlier.
出了什么事？外面真吵闹
It's nothing. Shall we eat now?
没事 我们吃饭吧
Come over and sit, Tsubasa.
-小翼 快点坐下 -菜色真豪华
Hurry, Tsubasa.
小翼 动作快
This is amazing.
很豪华喔
-Wow! -Right? They look delicious.
你看 看起来很美味吧
It looks so good.
看起来好好吃
Which dish shall I start with?
那么爸爸要先吃哪一道菜呢？
-Wow. -So tasty.
真好吃
They all taste so good.
每道菜都好美味
-Right, Tsubasa? -Yes!
-对吧 小翼？ -对啊
-Mita's really good at cooking! -You're right.
-三田 你真会煮菜 -就是说啊
I really wanted to eat food like these.
我就是想吃这种菜
I'm sorry that you always had to eat my bad cooking.
抱歉 总是帮你准备难吃的菜
You know I didn't mean it that way.
我又没说这种话
Right. Do you have a family, Mita?
对了 三田小姐 你有家人吗？
I had a husband and son.
我曾有过丈夫和儿子
That means...
你的意思是…
Have they perhaps passed away?
他们已经过世了吗？
Yes.
是的
My son was around the same age as Tsubasa.
我儿子过世时 正好是小翼先生现在的年纪
If you don't mind, could you share
如果你不介意的话 可以告诉我们
the reason why they passed away?
两人过世的原因吗？
Someone set fire to our house.
有人在我家纵火
What? By whom?
什么？是谁做的好事？
Mita. Could you get the cake out now?
三田 可以帮我拿蛋糕出来吗？
Understood.
我知道了
Happy birthday dear Tsubasa
祝你生日快乐 亲爱的小翼
Happy birthday to you
祝你生日快乐
-Can I? -Go ahead.
-我要吹了 -好
-Yay! -Happy birthday!
-太好了 吹熄了 -生日快乐
Hey, you! What are you doing?
等一下 你在做什么？
I'm pouring gasoline.
我在洒汽油
I'm asking why you're doing this!
我的意思是你为什么要这么做？
Ms. Minagawa ordered me to do so.
这是夫人的命令
She asked me to burn down the house, together with the whole family.
她要我烧死家里的所有人 还有这栋房子
What?
什么？
Did you ask her to do that?
你竟然拜托她做这种事？
It's your fault! It's all because you betrayed me!
都是你的错 你竟敢背叛我
Are you crazy?
你疯了吗？
What do you take Tsubasa's life for?
你有把小翼的生命放在眼里吗？
Don't just blame me!
别只会责备我
Besides...
再说…
I didn't expect her to do it for real.
我没料到她真的会做出这种事
Wait, stop it! Hey!
等一下 住手
-That hurt! -Papa!
-好痛 -爸爸
Stop!
住手！
What's with that look?
你那是什么表情？
I knew it. There's something wrong with you.
你果然精神不正常
You'd kill anyone without hesitation.
你竟然面不改色地杀人
You're so dangerous. Why don't you die for the sake of this world?
你这个人太危险了 为了这个社会 我看你去死算了
As you wish.
我知道了
Hey. What are you doing?
等一下 你在做什么？
Let's run, Tsubasa!
小翼 快跑
Hey! Wait! Wait for me!
等等 别抛下我
Run!
快逃
Stop, Mita!
三田小姐 住手
Mita!
三田小姐！
I'm sorry, but could you not interfere?
很抱歉 请不要阻碍我
I beg you! Please stop, Mita!
求求你住手 三田小姐
Get out! All of you will die if you don't.
快离开这里 否则你们也会没命
Mita...
三田小姐…
Are you fine with this?
这样好吗？
You'll really die.
你真的会死耶
I don't mind.
我不介意
Don't say that!
别说这种话
This has nothing to do with you.
这与你们无关
It has everything to do with us!
这与我们有关
I love you, Mita!
我最喜欢你了
Do you like me, Mita?
三田小姐 你喜欢我吗？
I...
我…
I'm stupid,
我脑袋不好
so I don't know what I should do now.
不知道该怎么做
But...
但是…
I just want to protect you, Mita!
我想要保护你
I...
我…
I'll rack my brains,
我会拼命想办法
and come up with a way for you to be happy, Mita!
设法让你获得幸福
I...
我…
No matter what you say,
不管你怎么说
I feel that we have all formed a family bond with one another!
但我认为我们和你之间 有着宛如家人的羁绊
Otherwise,
要不是这样…
you wouldn't have told us your terrible past!
你不会把惊人的过去告诉我们
So...
所以…
I don't ever want to let go of our bond!
我绝不想失去我们之间的羁绊
No...
不…
I won't let go, even if I die!
就算失去性命 我也不会放手
Just stop this already!
给我适可而止！
Please leave me alone already.
拜托你们别管我了
I...
我…
As a housekeeper,
身为家政妇
I only need to do what I'm ordered to.
只要完成主人的命令就好
Why?
为什么？
Why would you say that?
你为什么要说这种话？
I do not deserve to have a will of my own.
因为我不该拥有自己的意志
When I act on my own will,
如果我拥有自己的意志
everyone around me becomes unhappy.
我身边的人会变得不幸
All the people I love
我深爱的人
has left this world.
全都消失了
There is nothing left
我的心里
in my heart.
变得空荡荡
I simply need to
我只要像机器人一样
carry out orders, just like a robot.
完成命令就好
Is that why...
所以…
you're working as a housekeeper?
所以你才会成为家政妇吗？
I tried to die so many times, but it wouldn't work.
我试图寻死过好几次 却没有成功
When I act on my own will,
我依照自己的意志行事时
things just don't work out the way I want.
总是事与愿违
I've been waiting...
我一直在等待
for this day to come.
这一天的到来
Please, stop getting in my way!
拜托你们不要阻碍我
You're mistaken, Mita!
三田小姐 你错了
Our family...
我们一家人
Thanks to you...
多亏了你
We got over the pain of losing Mom.
才走出妈妈过世的伤痛
Isn't this because you wanted to help us
其实在你的心底深处
and wanted us to become happy
也想要拯救我们
I know that the pain and sadness you feel
我知道你经历的痛苦与悲伤
is nothing comparable to ours!
与我们无法相比
This time, we'll do what we can.
我们这次想要靠自己的力量
We want to save you, Mita!
让你获得救赎 三田小姐
Mita. Come fetch me at school again,
三田小姐 你再来幼儿园接我
and sing songs with me again!
我们再一起唱歌吧？
After climbing up this slope
爬上这座山丘之后
There's a tree to the right
往右边走有一棵树
When you turn at the tree and walk straight
在树的地方转弯 然后继续前进
Your beloved home is there waiting for you
你可爱的家在等着你
That's her! Hurry up and arrest her!
就是她 快点逮捕她
-Wait! There's a reason why she's... -Come with us!
-请等一下 这是基于许多原因… -过来
-Mita!
-三田小姐
SAKURADAI POLICE STATION
（樱台警察局）
Excuse me...
不好意思…
Are you all right?
你没事吧？
Don't worry, she's fine!
别担心 她没事
The police also heard what the wife had to say,
警察也询问过那户人家的妻子了
so they understood that it's just a marital fight.
发现原因是夫妻吵架
Besides, the husband said that it's his fault in the first place,
丈夫也承认自己有错在先
so they don't want to wash dirty linen in public.
不能再继续让家庭蒙羞了
I see.
这样啊
Please excuse me.
我先告辞了
Excuse me, Mita.
不好意思 三田小姐
I heard from the kids.
孩子们都告诉我了
They saw you get mad for the first time.
他们第一次看到你发脾气
Actually, I'm angry too.
我其实也很生气
You let my kids be in danger!
你竟然让我家的孩子身陷危险
They were trying to protect you with their lives!
他们为了保护你 不惜牺牲生命
Are you going to feign ignorance?
你却打算装作若无其事吗？
I'm sorry.
很抱歉
If you're sorry,
如果你感到抱歉
then take responsibility and work for us again.
请扛起责任 再次到我家工作
That's fine, right?
可以吗？
Oh, I'm totally fine with it.
我完全不介意
In return, we won't ask you to do anything that will trouble others
作为交换条件 我们不会再对你提出
or resort to any cowardly acts to shirk our own responsibility.
造成其他人的困扰 不负责任的卑鄙要求了
We want your help to make our family happy, Mita.
我希望你能让我们家人变得更幸福
If possible, we want you to be happy too.
我希望你也能获得幸福
If you're fine with that,
如果你不介意
could you please work for us again?
你可以再来我们家工作吗？
With your own will.
请用你自己的意志决定
Morning.
早安
-Good morning.
-早安 好了 -早安
Will Mita come?
三田小姐会来吗？
She will.
会的
Yeah.
对
Right.
没错
Guess Mita's not coming.
三田小姐果然没有来
I'll get the door!
我去开门
Hello. I'm Mita, the housekeeper.
大家好 我是家政妇 我姓三田
Excuse me, but are you here to work again?
不好意思 难道你又接到指派…
No, that's not it.
不是的
It seems like I left something here the other day.
我上次好像有东西忘在这里
Did you find a handkerchief?
各位看到一条手帕了吗？
Oh, did you mean this?
是这条手帕吗？
Sorry about this. Thank you!
不好意思 谢谢
Oh, one more thing.
对了 还有一件事
Anything else?
还有其他事情吗？
Akari's at the entrance.
灯子在门口
What?
什么？
Mita...
三田小姐
What are you doing? Just come in!
你在做什么？快点进来
Before that, can I confirm something?
在那之前 我想跟各位确认一件事
What is it?
什么事？
I am simply a housekeeper.
我只是一位家政妇
I am not part of your family.
不是各位的家人
We know.
我们清楚
I will not eat with all of you.
我不能跟各位一起用餐
I will not go out with all of you.
也不能跟各位一起外出
Also...
还有…
The only thing I will not do is smile.
就算各位要我笑 我也办不到
Are you fine with that?
各位能接受吗？
We understand.
没问题
Please excuse me.
打扰了
It looks so good.
看起来好好吃喔
Well then...
那么…
-Thank you for the food.
-我开动了
It's just so good!
果然好吃
Ouch!
好痛
What's wrong?
怎么了？
Mita!
三田小姐
Yes?
是
I got a splinter.
我被东西刺到了
Do you have a tweezer?
你有镊子吗？
I do.
有
Hey. Do you suppose that
就算我要求
she can pull out the most ridiculous items from that bag of hers?
不可能存在的东西 那个包包也变得出来吧
Try saying something.
那你试试看吧
Mita.
三田小姐
Yes?
是
Do you have medicine that will make me clever?
你有让我变聪明的药吗？
I don't have that.
没有
I knew it.
果然没有啊
Stupid.
蠢蛋
There's not way she'd have one.
当然不可能有啊
Then Mita.
三田小姐
Yes?
是
Do you have a photo of your husband and son?
你有丈夫和儿子的照片吗？
Oh, sorry. Forget about that.
抱歉 当我没说
If you don't hurry, you will be late for school.
动作快 否则各位会迟到
Oh, no!
惨了
-We're leaving!
-我们出门了
Have a safe trip.
路上小心
Let's go, Kii.
希衣 走吧
Good morning.
早安
Oh... You're back, Mita.
三田小姐 你回来啦
Then I don't need to worry anymore.
看来我可以放心了
I'm leaving Keiichi and the kids in your care.
姐夫他们就拜托你了
Also, please eat these.
还有这个请你吃
Did you make this for Mr. Asuda and the children?
这是你为主人他们做的吗？
Well... It's always like this.
这个嘛 我老是这样
I'm always unlucky, and things I do always backfire.
总是运气不好 做什么事情都适得其反
I'm just extremely unlucky.
每年都在犯太岁
Taxis won't appear right when I'm in a hurry,
赶时间的时候 总是拦不到出租车
and I fall off the stairs when I visit a shrine to ward off bad luck.
当我去神社除厄运时 总会摔下楼梯
The computer and fax machine also breaks down when I use it.
被我碰过的电脑和传真机都会故障
Even when I go out with guys, I always pull the shorter end of the stick
交往过的男人没一个好东西
and fall for the losers.
总是遇到烂男人
What are you trying to say?
您到底想说什么？
Mita...
三田小姐
I think I'm in love with Keiichi.
我好像爱上姐夫了
I know it's dumb, but I just can't control it any longer.
我清楚自己的愚蠢 但我已经无法自拔了
What am I saying?
我在胡说什么啊？
Please forget about that.
请当我没说
Also, could you not tell that to everyone?
还有请千万不要把这件事 告诉任何人
I will never come here again.
我不会再过来了
See you.
再见
Your cooking is tasty as always, Mommy.
妈妈 你煮的菜总是这么好吃
We're really lucky, aren't we?
我们真的很幸福 对吧？
We get to eat delicious food every day.
每天都能吃到这么美味的菜肴
Yeah!
对啊
-You should eat more vegetables, too. -Okay.
-要多吃蔬菜喔 -好
Let me take some for you.
我帮你夹
Mommy. Let's go to the amusement park together again!
妈妈 我们下次再一起去游乐园玩吧
Right. Shall we go this coming Sunday, Akari?
就这么办 这周日就去吧？
The two of you are angry that
你们两个在生我的气
I'm the only one happy, right?
因为只有我一个人过得幸福 对吧？
No matter what you do,
不论你做什么
you always make everyone around you unhappy.
你总是会给你身边的人带来不幸
Stop blaming yourself.
别再责备自己了
Let's go home.
我们回家吧
I cannot return to how I once was
我已经无法回到
before my husband and son died!
我老公和小孩去世前的那个我
Subtitle translation by: Qianni Lu
字幕翻译：吴敬美